{
  "reference_number": "12642",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "Climate change in unequivocally real and the most fundamental issue facing New Zealand and the world. This is not a partisan issue,\n we cannot continue to have governments setting regulatory targets and changing them as political capital changes, targets and\n processes must be enacted in statute"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "In order to avoid catastrophic climate shift, the world needs to limit warming to 2 degrees, this means every country needs to do its\n\n utmost to reduce emissions. Targets should be best case, especially for a country that markets itself as an environmental leader.\n There is no point in setting a low target, frankly the best target is zero gross emissions. Failing that net zero emissions is the next\n\n best thing. We need to do all we can, even if we fall short, this is not something we as a species can ignore or equivocate on."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "If the international sector has taught us anything in the last two years, it is that we cannot rely on major powers to take a stand for the\n environment. New Zealand needs to be a leader not a follower in this area, including living up to our Paris Agreement obligations and\n entreating our allies and international partners to do the same."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "We cannot, as a species, continue to equivocate and push climate action down the line. There is no end of the line. We need broad\n\n bold action. We do not have another planet to go to, no matter what people try to claim, the only solution is for leaders to take a\n stand, this is the eleventh hour."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "However only changes that further reduce targets should be considered in all but the most dire circumstances. This does not mean\n\n an incoming government should reduce targets because fonterra stock prices has dropped. These targets should be reduced if\n absolutely necessary to preserve human life in the face of disaster. It must be remembered that political and social problems,\n however serious will mean nothing if there is no world for our children to inherit. That is the time-scale now, our children, not distant\n\n descendants, for many not even Grandchildren, it is the next generation who will suffer."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "See above"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Consider the whole process, do not set broad, high-minded policy, work from the top to the bottom to ensure it is carried out."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Range of expertise should not include climate change deniers for the sake of diversity, ensure those involved are not involved for\npolitical or financial reasons"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "In the Pacific we, and our closest neighbours, are most vulnerable to climate change, no matter what steps are taken there are going\nto be consequences and we must be prepared"
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
